Hello everyone and welcome back
to English Pod, my name is Marco.
My name is Catherine
and today we're talking
about one of our
favorite subjects, food.
That's right and on
this occasion we are
going to talk about Chinese
food specifically stir fry.
Okay, this is a common
dish in America and all
over the world thanks
to the many Cantonese
people who came over
from Hong Kong or southern
China and brought these
delicious foods to our cities.
So this is a very popular dish
you'll be learning more about.
So let's jump right
in and listen to today's
dialogue and don't
be worried if you don't
understand everything
we'll be back in a moment.
Oh man, I had the best supper last night.
My wife made a stir fry and it was amazing.
I love stir fry.
Just be bite-sized
vegetables covered in a
mixture of soy sauce and oyster sauce,
wilted greens and fresh beans sprouts.
Throw in some onion and garlic and
ginger, mmm, mmm, it's almost lunch time.
I would die for a plate
of stir fry right now.
Well, you can keep the
vegetables, I'll take the meat.
The stir fry my wife
made was really hearty
with chunks of beef and
slivers of bell peppers and onion.
What?
You call that a stir fry?
Or make the vegetables,
that's the worst
insult you could throw
at a Chinese stir fry.
What a disgrace to the wok she fried it in.
What you had is equivalent
to a fajita without the wrap.
All right, we're back
so you probably heard
a lot of different vegetables
and ingredients in this dish.
So why don't we take a look at some
of those now in language takeaway?
Language takeaway.
The first two phrases
that we have actually,
they're not words,
they're phrases, are the
names of sauces that are very,
very important to Chinese food.
The first one is soy sauce.
Okay, soy sauce and
it's this black sauce, right?
Very salty.
Very salty and it's made from soy beans.
Soy beans, okay.
Soy, so soy is a bean, a vegetable product,
but soy sauce is a thin black salty sauce.
Okay, and it's very, very common to
use it with Chinese dishes especially.
It's very related and usually
have sushi with soy sauce.
Exactly, so Japanese
food is a lot of this too.
All right, and the
other sauce that's not
very common in our
countries is oyster sauce.
Okay, and oyster is an animal that lives in
the sea, it lives in a shell and we often
eat oysters as a dish, but oyster sauce
is stinky, thick, dark sauce that is very
popular in Southeast Asia, so
Vietnamese food as well and Chinese food.
Okay, so it's part of the
ingredients of Chinese food.
It's really good.
It smells terrible, but
when you mix it with
food and you cook it, it smells
as a very, very good flavor.
Absolutely.
All right, so that's the sauces.
Now, apart from sauces, we have some
vegetables and some of those are bean sprouts.
Bean sprouts are very
common vegetables, especially
in Asian foods, so
you see a lot of these
they're usually almost
white, almost clear and
they're crunchy and they have
a little green part at the end.
Right, so they're like little straws
with a little green point at the end.
So usually those go into your dish at
the very end because they cook quickly.
Bean sprouts.
Okay, now if you're
cooking stir-fry, what you
need is the correct tools and the
main tool that you need is a wok.
That's right, so a wok is actually a word
that we take from, I think, Cantonese.
I'm not positive.
I don't speak Cantonese,
but in English, we
normally say frying
pan, but this is a special
Asian frying pan that's
very, very large and
very thin, so foods
cook quickly in a wok.
Okay, and it's not like the other
pans where it has a big flat part.
It's very, very round all over.
That's right, it's almost
like a bowl that sits
on your stove and you
cook quickly in a wok.
So that's a wok.
And while the guy compared his stir-fry to
a phahida, now phahida, that's not Chinese.
And it's not English.
Okay.
Well, it is English now.
It's actually the name of
a food from Latin America.
So South America and Mexico and Central
America, I think more Mexican than anything.
And it's like slivers of
meat, so thin strips of
meat and vegetables that
you eat in a tortilla bread.
So it's like very thin
corn or flour pancake.
Yeah.
So that's a phahida.
It's kind of, you've
probably seen it a
phahida or a, or maybe
what's commonly known as
well as a burrito, which actually
is also an American invention.
I don't think that exists in Mexico.
No, but they are delicious.
I think the word is Tex-Mex.
Tex-Mex.
All right.
So that's what we have for you on language.
Take away why don't we
go back to our dialogue,
listen to it again, and
we'll be back shortly.
Oh man, I had the best supper last night.
My wife made a stir-fry and it was amazing.
I love stir-fry.
Crispy bite-sized vegetables
covered in a mixture
of soy sauce and oyster
sauce, wilted greens
and fresh beans sprouts, throw in
some onion and garlic and ginger.
Mm, it's almost lunch time.
I would die for a plate
of stir-fry right now.
Well, you can keep the vegetables.
I'll take the meat.
The stir-fry my wife
made was really hardy
with chunks of beef and
slivers of bell peppers and onion.
What?
You call that a stir-fry?
More meat than vegetables?
That's the worst insult you
could throw at a Chinese stir-fry.
What a disgrace to
the walk she fried it in.
What you had is equivalent
to a fajita without the wrap.
All right, we're back.
So now, I think we
should take a look at some
of those phrases that were used
in this dialogue in fluency builder.
Fluency builder.
The first phrase we
have in fluency builder
is a phrase that you will hear often
when you watch cooking shows.
So this is a term we
say throw in to throw in.
Okay, so throw in some vegetables
or throw in some onion and garlic.
And that means to just put it into the pan.
Put it into the pot.
That's right.
But it's very general or casual or easy.
You just add some.
If you want to be specific, we can
say, please add one cup chopped onion.
Okay.
One cup of chopped onion.
But here's the throw in
just means add casually.
Okay.
Add some onion.
Throw in all of this
ingredients and it
sounds so delicious
that the guy says, I would
die for a plate of
stir-fry right about now.
Mm.
So that means he wants some stir-fry.
I would die for is a good thing.
It's a way to say I really want some.
It's an exaggeration.
It's not like you would actually
die for it or you were dying to eat it.
It's just that it's an exaggeration
means that you really, really want it.
I would die for a new car.
My car is old and it never really works.
All right.
I really want a new car.
Mm-hmm.
Okay.
And well, the guy
obviously didn't really like
what he was talking
about and how he cooked
this stir-fry and he said, what a
disgrace to the walk she frided in.
Okay.
This is a way to say that something is bad.
It's embarrassing.
So we can say that
this food is a disgrace to
Chinese food because
Chinese food is one way.
But this doesn't even
look like Chinese food.
So a disgrace.
They disagree.
So the word disgrace, it
means that something is bad.
Or embarrassing to something else.
So a parent can say, you're
a disgrace to this family.
That means this family
has a good reputation.
But what you did, what
you do, these are bad things.
They make us look bad.
They're embarrassing.
They're embarrassing to us.
Okay.
So it's a very strong phrase.
This is a disgrace.
Okay.
A disgrace.
Very good.
A strong phrase.
Talk about someone
or something in this way.
But remember, it is pretty strong.
Right?
If you say somebody's a
disgrace, it's pretty insulting.
It's hurtful.
Okay.
So why don't we listen to our dialogue
for one last time and we'll be back.
Oh man, I had the best supper last night.
My wife made a stir-fry and it was amazing.
I love stir-fry.
Let's be bite-sized vegetables covered in
a mixture of soy sauce and oyster sauce.
Will to greens and fresh beans sprouts?
Throw in some onion and garlic and ginger.
Mm.
It's almost lunch time.
I would die for a plate
of stir-fry right now.
Well, you can keep the vegetables.
I'll take the meat.
The stir-fry my wife
made was really hearty
with chunks of beef and
slivers of bell peppers and onion.
What?
You call that a stir-fry?
More meat than vegetables?
It's the worst insult you could
throw at a Chinese stir-fry.
What a disgrace to the wok she fried it in.
What you had is equivalent
to a fajita without the wrap.
All right, so talking
about Chinese food,
there are a lot of
American inventions around
Chinese food as well,
not only Mexican food.
For example, it's very
popular this dish chopped sui.
That's right.
And I think I read
somewhere that chopped sui
is actually, might have
been a Cantonese dish
that came from all of
the leftovers and kind
of garbage in the
kitchen, where you would
just fry it together and
it was a cheap, easy meal.
Mm-hmm.
So chopped sui, it's kind of like
an English, it's like a pigeon English.
And well, this dish is
basically that, right?
It's just a lot of meat
chunks mixed with
some vegetables and you
have some chopped sui.
Exactly.
And there are also
this other thing that's
very common people
think about fortune cookies.
You think of Chinese restaurants and
Chinese food, you think of fortune cookies.
That's right.
But they don't have
fortune cookies in China.
No, they do.
One of my biggest disappointments.
So fortune cookie is
a small cookie with a
message inside, so you
have a piece of paper.
So be careful when you're eating these.
You don't want to eat the paper.
But the paper sometimes
says very strange
things, like you will have
a terrific number seven.
Right or something like that.
So that's why they're fortune cookies.
They usually talk about your
future or what you're talking about.
Beware of whales.
So, but that's also
an American invention
that doesn't exist in China, it
doesn't really come from China, right?
Exactly.
So if you have any other information about
food, or we're always glad to hear it.
Because we're always hungry.
Or if you have a favorite
Chinese food, please let us know.
Our website is EnglishPod.com.
We can't wait to hear from you
and we will talk to you next time.
Bye.
[MUSIC]